Hector Olea

Full Stack Developer

hectorolea.dev

+52 449 222 4412

hey@hectorolea.dev

• Aguascalientes, Mexico

Key skills

Soft skills

Teamwork, Problem-solving, Adaptability, Collaborative learning, Integrity, Motivation, and Responsibility

Backend

Java, Spring Boot,
Microservices, REST APIs,
Python, Node JS, Oracle
Database, PLSQL, Spring Data
JPA, Apache Kafka, JUnit,
Mockito, MongoDB, Maven,
Gradle, Mocha, Chai, GraphQL

Frontend

React + TypeScript, Redux, Hooks, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Jest, JavaScript, TanStack Query, Astro, Tailwind

Dev0ps

Kubernetes, Docker, Github,
Jenkins, Sonar, Bash
scripting, GNU/Linux, CI/CD

Monitoring

Graphite, Grafana, Xmatters, Spotlight, Service Now

Misc

Agile, Scrum, Test Pyramid, Hexagonal Architecture, Test-Driven Development, Domain-Driven Design, SOLID Principles, Clean Code, DevOps

Languages

English - Proficient

Spanish - Native/Bilingual

Profile

I am a Full Stack Developer with a DevOps mindset. I enjoy learning about new technologies, programming languages, and frameworks.

I have 13+ years of experience in the IT industry, where I have gained skills as a Full Stack Developer, Site Reliability Engineer, and DevOps.

My expertise includes developing, maintaining, and supporting web applications and microservices using Java, Python, NodeJS, React, and Spring Boot. In addition, I am familiar with Agile software development like Clean Code, Test Pyramid, Hexagonal Architecture, DevOps, TDD, DDD, and Scrum. Furthermore, I have experience in automating operational tasks and monitoring applications for operation teams.

Professional Experience

Software Engineer, IBM - D&B

Dec 2023 - Mar 2024

- Supported and maintained a Financial Analytics application.
- Attended incidents and tasks raised at ServiceNow.

Full Stack Developer, IBM - Discover

Feb 2023 - Jul 2023 | Aguascalientes, Mexico

- Developed microservice to merge related customer database information given an SSN identifier.
- Added features to microservices responsible for storing cases and product information.
- Applied Sonar suggestions to existing microservices to improve the quality of the software components.
- Added init tests to existing microservices to further enhance the software components' quality.

Full Stack Developer, Softtek - Walmart

Sep 2020 - Dec 2022 | Aguascalientes, Mexico

- Maintained, supported, and developed new features for 15 microservices created in Sprint Boot and NodeJS.
- Created bash and python scripts for daily basis support tasks.
- Migrated successfully to the Walmart Cloud Native platform, resulting in reduced costs, deployment time, auto-scaling, and improved maintainability.
- Migrated Event Hubs and Armory to Apache Kafka for more resilient services and to reduce missing events.
- Implemented fault-tolerant approaches for HTTP clients and databases.
- Reduced technical debts on microservices, ranking as the top team out of 100 in DevOps best practices.
- Learned about hexagonal architecture, test pyramid, clean code practices, and a DevOps mindset.

Certificates

Scrum Fundamentals Certified

Java EE 6 Web Component Developer Certified Expert

Oracle Certified Professional, Java SE 6 Programmer

Education

Computer Systems Engineering, Instituto Tecnológico de Acapulco

2003 - 2008 | Acapulco, Mexico

Courses

Microservices: Clean Architecture, DDD, SAGA, Outbox & Kafka

Master Java Web Services and RESTful API with Spring Boot

Apache Kafka for Developers using Spring Boot

Master Java Unit Testing with Spring Boot & Mockito

Master Hibernate and JPA with Spring Boot in 100 steps

Node with React: Fullstack Web Development

Go Java Full Stack with Spring Boot and React

React: From scratch to expert (Hooks y MERN)

TanStack Query: A powerful asynchronous state manager

GraphQL with React: The
Complete Developers Guide

Astro: The framework for content-oriented websites

SOLID principles: Introducing Software Architecture & Design

- Fixed critical vulnerabilities by upgrading the old spring boot version to the latest version, changing the docker-base images, and upgrading project dependencies.
- Implemented an application authentication approach for creating, updating, and deleting endpoints for microservices using Service Registry and Service Mesh, and generated proper HTTP headers and authentication signatures.

Site Reliability Engineer, Softtek - Southwest Airlines

Aug 2017 - Sep 2020 | Aguascalientes, Mexico

- Automated processes to reduce repetitive tasks for the operations team.
- Developed Python and bash scripts to automate services, manage Grafana dashboard inventory, generate Monthly Reports, and send metrics to Graphite.
- Developed a dynamic dashboard using Spring Boot and React JS to monitor Tivoli jobs and detect issues early.
- Created REST APIs to automate incident management in Service Now.
- Used an image recognition tool (Sikuli) to automate manual tasks for legacy C applications.

Java Web Developer, Softtek - General Electric 2015 - 2017 | Aguascalientes, Mexico

- Maintained an application that can retrieve transactions from text plain files through FTP interfaces.
- Supported and monitored a complex core made in Java that was processing more than 400k transactions once a
- Tuned SQL queries and PL/SQL procedures in an Oracle database.
- Implemented SQL Loader to quickly load and save thousands of transactions.

Delphi/Visual Basic/Java Developer, INEGI

Mar 2010 - May 2015 | Aguascalientes, Mexico

- Maintained the state and municipal database system (SIMBAD) which presented the census information from Mexico.
- Developed a portable installer for the SIMBAD that could be used in multiple states of Mexico for sharing statistics.
- Supported and maintained an interpreter of questionnaires, which was capable of loading XML definitions to create UI components, SQLite databases, and resources in real-time.
- Developed simulators to train the operative figures in the population census 2010 and trained and supervised the operative figures of the population and housing census.